<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Eric Jones</title>
		<description>Eric Jones builds software, travels by bicycle, and is only slightly obsessed with maps.</description>
		<link>http://www.ercjns.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.ercjns.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Fake News</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been dreaming about ideas for a simple but off-hand useful twitter bot, and #fakenews became an opportunity. Most people who have taken an intro computer science course are familiar with markov chains. Without getting too technical, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;markov chain&lt;/a&gt; is a process where the next outcome in the process, given the current state, is independent of past behavior, and where the possible outcomes are discrete known values. This algorithm turns out to be a great way to generate text that reads in a specific voice. (This isn’t a new trick - there are plenty of markov text generators around the web.)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/01/18/fake-news.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/01/18/fake-news.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Torres del Paine Beta</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Planning a trip to Torres del Paine? Here’s a quick overview of my trip backpacking the full in December 2016, and some things I would have liked to have known while planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I also wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;/travel/2016/12/15/chile.html&quot;&gt;full trip journal&lt;/a&gt; that I hope you’ll enjoy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/torres-lnt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Leave No Trace. Ama Torres Del Paine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;getting-there&quot;&gt;Getting There&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Located at pretty much at the end of the world, it’s appropriate that getting to Torres isn’t exactly easy. But it’s not that difficult, it just takes time. Puerto Natales is the launch point for any trip into the park. During the high season, you can fly direct from Santiago. If it’s the off season, fly from Santiago to Punta Arenas, then catch a bus. The buses from Punta Arenas to Puerto Natales run almost every hour, all day long. (We were able to walk up and buy seats for the next bus, but it’s safer to buy tickets a day ahead if you can.) If you’re taking more time exploring Patagonia, you might be coming from Argentina, or taking the ferry from Puerto Mott to Puerto Natales. Without any experience to back it up, both sound like great options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puerto Natales has everything you need to supply your trip - there are a number of outfitters and there is one larger chain grocery store, though I didn’t visit it. If you can, use the smaller independent shops in town. Many stores sell fuel canisters, but check at your hostel first to snag unused fuel from folks just off the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of bus companies from Puerto Natales into the park. They all run just about the same schedules. We used Buses Gomez, and have no complaints. I’m sure they’re all fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;camping&quot;&gt;Camping&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt; to have camping reservations. It’s a way to keep the crowds somewhat manageable (but oh boy is it still &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; crowded, especially considering how remote the location really is). Figure out your itinerary early and make camping reservations as soon as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we booked for the full circuit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serón&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dickson&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paso&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paine Grande&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italiano&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Torres&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical itinerary for the circuit would include an additional night at Perros, and possibly replace Paso with Grey. (An alternate six night itinerary skips Dickson for Perros, and replaces Paso with Grey.) For hiking the W, most recommendations are to hike from West to East, but really there’s no wrong way to do it, although bus timings likely work better this direction. What do all these names mean? You’ll need a map for that…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;maps&quot;&gt;Maps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The map you get from the park when you pay the entry fee is actually quite good. Here’s a photo of my copy: &lt;a href=&quot;/res/TorresDelPaineParkMap.pdf&quot;&gt;Torres del Paine CONAF Map 2016 Front&lt;/a&gt; (18MB pdf).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trails are all well marked on the map and in the terrain, and you’re not allowed to leave them, so this is more than adequate for navigation. You can find a number of versions of the map online, some better than others. Beware that the latest version (as of this writing) has some changes that are not marked on most of the online maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can’t do the “Q” in the summer - the trail from Adminstration to Paine Grande is closed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many maps show a trail directly from Laguna Amarga to Serón, but it no longer exists. You can walk the road, or take a shuttle to Torres Central for CLP3000.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can only walk the backside from East to West: Seron -&amp;gt; Dickson -&amp;gt; Perros -&amp;gt; Paso -&amp;gt; Grey. You’ll be turned back at ranger stations if you don’t have the right reservation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From Cuernos, the “shortcut” trail to Chileno is signed and cuts off before (to the West of) the small lake on the map. It appears there is a trail at the marked location east of the lake, but we didn’t notice it join the trail we were on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;food--cooking&quot;&gt;Food / Cooking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find reasonable backpacking fare in Puerto Natales, though if you have specific requests you’ll do much better in Punta Arenas or Santiago. For us, breakfast and lunch were typically granola / muesli mixed with dried fruits and peanut butter, and dinner was pasta with salami and cheese. The map is a bit confusing on this, but yes, every campsite has a cooking shelter where you can use your stove. The cooking shelters are also the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; places you can use your stove, so pack a thermos if you want a hot beverage after leaving camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming from bear country, the lack of guidelines for food storage was a bit boggling. We saw and used a variety of strategies. Most popular is to simply keep food with you in your tent. We also hung food from trees as well as from a trekking pole tripod. The threat is mice, but we saw little evidence and had no problems with any of these strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;water&quot;&gt;Water&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone will tell you to just drink the water from streams, and that’s probably sound advice. I brought a filter because I don’t like giardia, but to be honest I didn’t use it 100% of the time. In an odd twist of back-country amenities, some of the camps have rigged up running water systems to provide flush toilets (!) and sinks / taps. For my stance, I’d say it’s much more important to boil or filter water you collect from the tap or other in-camp sources than to worry about filtering stream water away from camp. Water sources are fairly regular but not everywhere. You could probably get by with only one liter of capacity if you filled up at every opportunity, but you’ll be happier carrying two liters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;trails&quot;&gt;Trails&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s busy - everything is well marked and well trodden. That doesn’t mean it’s easy. You’re carrying food for seven days, and in places there are steep ascents and descents. Lots of reports warn of wind, and while we didn’t experience any prolonged strong winds, I believe the warnings. The worst trail conditions we encountered were descending from John Gardner Pass into the Paso campsite. Once you reach the tree line, the trail becomes &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; steep with makeshift handrails made from all different materials: rope, rebar, wood and PVC to name a few. Nothing else stands out as particularly notable, but here’s a few more tidbits. The trail on the east leading up to the pass is rocky but well marked. The swing brides north of Grey are long and extremely high, but at appear new-ish and well built. If you’re afraid of heights, well, don’t look down. Most (but not all) boggy areas have some sort of boardwalk, but this wouldn’t be backpacking if you didn’t get your boots dirty. Do you best to walk through mud puddles in the middle of the trail so as to not expand the trail into the terrain more than necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More coming soon…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/travel/2016/12/16/torres-beta.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/travel/2016/12/16/torres-beta.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Chile</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Seven days on the full circuit in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torres_del_Paine_National_Park&quot;&gt;Torres del Paine National Park&lt;/a&gt; and a few other southern hemisphere adventures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I also have a page with &lt;a href=&quot;/travel/2016/12/16/torres-beta.html&quot;&gt;trail beta&lt;/a&gt; if that’s what you’re looking for.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-01-pass-pano.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking West to Grey Glacier and the Patagonia Ice Sheet from John Gardner Pass&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;29-november-2016&quot;&gt;29 November, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m waiting for my first flight in the Atlanta airport’s new international terminal. It’s a lofty white atmosphere with blue accents and much more natural light than other areas of ATL which can be extremely dull. Of course, after a few minutes I notice that here too the lack of flavor is unfortunate. (Even all the official signage is light grey on dark grey, no color at all.) The crowds here all appear very American except for the flight crew from Qatar making their way to a nearby gate. A pleasant surprise is the lack of PA announcements, but it only reinforces the corporate atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flight to Toronto is only half full. Just after takeoff, we pass through some strong turbulence. I can make out thunderheads lit from below by the suburban sprawl. Soon the ride settles out, and thankfully the baby one row behind me calms down as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear as we arrive in Toronto. The CN Tower is lit modestly; the rest of the city looks crisp in the cool night air. A mix of orange and white streetlights stretch out to the horizon. The terminal is dark, which is appropriate as it’s nearing eleven PM. We clear passport control and continue to our connecting gate. Only after boarding the 777 do I start hearing the spanish all around me. I’ll do my best to sleep on this ten hour journey to the Southern Hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;30-november-2016&quot;&gt;30 November, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 40 minutes from landing in Santiago, I wake up and slide my window open. Outside, I see mountains bathing in bright sunshine, snowcapped and majestic. I hadn’t slept well. A number of crying children and a consistently bumpy ride never allowed me to get real sleep, although I’m not sure what I expected. My body hasn’t yet decided if the fact that there is only a two hour time difference between Atlanta and Santiago is good or bad, but I’m currently not excited for another three hours of flying later today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dumping our plane snacks from America and clearing customs, we are surrounded by drivers hounding for a fare into the city. Most speak good english, but we turn them down - we’re not looking for a ride. After checking bags for this afternoon’s flight, we get on a bus into town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beautiful views from 10,000 feet are now completely hidden by a blanket of smog. Speeding into town, sports fields fill the space between the highway and frontage roads. The pavement is full, mostly small sedans and buses, but also plenty of mopeds. We get off in a commercial district on the fringe of downtown and start to wander. School children enjoy their lunch and ice cream under trees in a park. Walking through a college campus there’s a non-zero chance of being hit by a stray water balloon. We’re clearly foreign, but never bothered. The storefronts on one street are selling electric motors of every shape and size. We buy some food for the rest of the trip (we’re unsure what sort of supplies are available in Punta Arenas and Puerto Natales, or if there is a significant markup) and catch the bus back to the airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-02-flying.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mountains below while flying south from Santiago to Punta Arenas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the air above Santiago, I can’t help but notice that the plane I’m riding in certainly isn’t helping all that smog. As we head further south, the mountainous terrain shifts from desert to forest to snowcapped peaks. Haze and high-altitude clouds play tricks with the afternoon sun to create two horizon lines. The snowcapped peaks shift back into forested land, still rugged, and now dotted with lakes all begging to be explored. The shadows grow long and peaks shine in the golden light. The last hour is less eventful - clouds blanket the terrain and it’s getting dark. As we slip under the clouds and see a tanker in the Straight of Magellan on the approach to Punta Arenas, my buddy takes in the view as twilight fades and rain falls: “Depressing, isn’t it?” I’m thinking just the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-december-2016&quot;&gt;1 December, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like town is still waking up as we wander from our hostel to the grocery store. Now in the light it’s still hard to get a feel for Punta Arenas. I wouldn’t classify anything as run down, but there isn’t anything new or flashy either. We’ll get a better understanding of town when we pass through after coming off the trail. In the grocery store we gather some looks but no trouble as we collect food we’ll be able to pack. We’re only slow because we don’t have a plan - the store is a fully stocked grocery. I’m surprised that even with a bag packed full of food, the stray dogs are just as lethargic as they were earlier; not a single one lifts even an eye as we pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I purchase bus tickets in only slightly fumbled spanish and we’re soon on our way to Puerto Natales. While the plane from Santiago was mostly Chilenos, today’s bus is mostly foreigners. It’s overcast with rain off and on as we pass through the rolling windswept terrain. Long stretches of straight pavement don’t exactly help the monotony, and after a few naps I’m happy to see peaks on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-03-natales.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View from the waterfront in Puerto Natales&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The business district in Puerto Natales has an oddly American feel. Checking in at our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.erraticrock.com/hostel/&quot;&gt;hostel&lt;/a&gt; is honestly a bit too comfortable: our host is from Minnesota and everyone here speaks english, but on the plus side we’re able to catch a great &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.erraticrock.com/equipment/info-seminars-1/&quot;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; about hiking in the park at the gear store right next door. One more afternoon of wandering before we hit the trail results in dried fruit and a variety of nuts from a hole in the wall shop, almost getting blown off a dock, and our first real encounter with a stray dog. Town shifts from shopping to dinner where we’re seated with a great view of a chef roasting a whole lamb over an open fire. We’re satisfied and head to bed early, excited and anxious to get on the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-december-2016&quot;&gt;2 December, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mattress felt like a box spring last night, so I’m thrilled to wake up for breakfast at 6:15am. We share eggs and granola at the hostel with others also headed into the park today, then make our way to the bus station. It’s a bit of a mad house: there are at least three different bus companies headed into the park all leaving at the same time, some with multiple loads. We get our bags on and find seats for another two hours of sitting. Luckily the terrain is much more interesting now, but the early morning sun turns the bus into a greenhouse, fogging up the windows to the West. The road turns to gravel, but we continue to speed along despite the bumpy ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the outskirts of the park, we’re treated to a reminder that we’re in the southern hemisphere. There are about 50 wild flamingos standing on the banks of a nearly dry lake bed. To be honest, the scene looks like it’s straight out of a North American zoo, except there’s a distinct lack of terrible food and children in strollers. We turn another corner and the park’s namesake rock formation are before us. I can’t resist snapping a few photos even though I know we’ll get much better opportunities outside the bus. In just a few more minutes we’re dropped at the Laguna Amarga ranger station to pay the entrance fee, receive a park map, and watch a quick orientation video (don’t make fire!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t even have our packs on before we have a bit of a surprise - this year’s map is missing a trail that is marked on previous versions we had seen online. No worries, we’ll walk the road which should only add an hour or two to an already short first day. The road undulates through the terrain as we get closer and closer to Las Torres and as we crest a hill, we can see green domes and some other buildings in the valley below us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We make it onto actual trail, but it doesn’t feel like backcountry. We pass groups of day hikers and other backpackers what seems like every ten minutes. The forest is like no forest I’ve seen before: it’s moderately dense with a few types of trees each sporting small leaves, none particularly tall, and a blanket of grasses below. Not long after we leave a gate open (as we found it), some horses approach us headed the opposite direction, no other human in sight. Hours later in the river valley a rancher passes by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-04-seron-valley.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View from the trail looking north into the valley where Seron campsite is located&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to call Serón a campsite, but honestly I had no idea what to expect. The host lives in a building with running water and what appears to be an industrial kitchen, a generator, and a satellite dish. There’s some food and beer for sale, albeit at an extremely high (appropriate) markup. We show our permit and set up camp in the field around the outpost. Anton and I meet a couple from Norway while cooking dinner on the porch. It’s still light out as we head to bed. The parrot in the tree above our tent and the music and generator from the outpost don’t help. I make some mental notes about new tent placement strategies and eventually fall asleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-december-2016&quot;&gt;3 December, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It rained a bit overnight, but the ground outside, as well as the food we left hanging in a nearby tree, is surprisingly dry. It seems like we’re one of the first few groups out of camp, but it’s hard to tell for sure. Low level clouds occasionally sprinkle rain as we make our way up the river valley. The trail is maybe a bit less crowded than yesterday as there are no day hikers from the Torres Central hotel, but we continue to see groups at least every half hour. Everyone is headed the same direction at this point (as mandated by park rules) so later in the day we intermingle with the same few groups hiking roughly the same speed. The fog and moisture brings out the greens as we cross through plains, forests, and rocky hillsides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-05-above-lago-paine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking west into fog and mountains from the trail above Lago Paine, about to re-enter park property&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a final short climb, the buildings in the meadow below us look just like an old west US military outpost, complete with a Chilean flag on an improvised pole. A couple icebergs populate the corner of the river, and despite being battered by wind and waves, they don’t budge, likely stuck on rocks below. Eventually we decide that yes, there really is a glacier hiding in the fog across the lake to the north. The views from every direction at Dickson are so different than what we saw on the east side of the park, it’s great to have another day under our belts with time to explore the area, enjoy the colors dancing on the rock faces above camp, and rest our feet before a long day tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-06-dickson-sketch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketch of Dickson&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-december-2016&quot;&gt;4 December, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re up early to get a good jump on the long day ahead, and luckily it looks like yesterday’s clouds are clearing out. We’re much more efficient taking down camp and decide to get a bit up the trail before taking breakfast. We pause where the forest opens up for a bit revealing a view to the North. The morning light and blue sky create glistening, crisp lines on the glacier. Continuing up the valley the forest is so lush and full of unfamiliar plants that at one point I’m sure I’m in a video game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-07-perros-lookout.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Different colored peaks through the trees at Valle Los Perros Lookout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words can’t begin to describe the beauty of the terrain we pass through, but there’s one other thing that helps: we haven’t encountered a single other group on the trail. After a break in the shade at the Perros ranger station, we’re fueled up for the steep climb ahead. While it’s hard to tell exactly where the pass is from below, the view down the valley continues to expand. It’s hard to believe how much ground we’ve covered - Dickson is hidden around a ridge far in the distance. Every few minutes the rocks change color and size, but we simply continue up, up, up. Soon enough, I feel a cool wind picking up strength and the saddle is just ahead of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-08-pass-rocks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Climbing John Gardner Pass&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few moments of standing in awe, reality catches up and we seek out a windbreak to enjoy the solitude at the top of John Gardner pass. Directly ahead are peaks, some volcanoes, but more impressive is Glacier Grey below, feeding Lago Grey which we can see to the south and extending from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Patagonian_Ice_Field&quot;&gt;Southern Patagonian Ice Sheet&lt;/a&gt; to the north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-09-pass-pano.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view from John Gardner Pass&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the trail literature warns about the way down from the pass, and they aren’t kidding. I can’t afford to allow the view to steal my focus away from the trail. As we descend, sometimes we find makeshift handrails: rope tied between trees or leftover rebar from anchoring steps. We’re having trouble judging our speed. We’ve been able to complete most sections in about 75% of the quoted time on the map, but this downhill is wrecking us. Just as we’re about to take a break in anticipation of another hour of hiking, we turn a corner to find the Paso ranger station and campsite nestled into the hillside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camp is very small compared to the others we’ve seen. There is a stream that flows through the tent pads and we immediately choose to set up near it for the benefit of white noise. There’s space for only about twenty tents and not much common area or space for wandering. As it turns out, we’re only joined by two other groups for the evening. The forest is thick, but if you squint you can make out the glacier below. As the sun falls, shadows dance on the broken icy surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-december-2016&quot;&gt;5 December, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forest here is different yet again; trees grow out of the slope at the horizontal, sometimes turning upward but often just reaching out. We move quickly on good trail that playfully bounces up and down in and around fissures on the hillside. Before too long we’re at the first of two swing bridges. This one looks like it’s straight out of a cartoon: maybe 75 meters long crossing a chasm with sheer faces so deep I can’t see the bottom except when I’m on the bridge. I know I looked down once, but I don’t have anything more than a vague recollection of rushing water and boulders &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; far below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-10-swing-bridge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crossing a swing bridge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday’s solitude is gone as we meet a number of dayhikers from Grey out to explore the bridges and get a view of the glacier from above. By the time we arrive at Grey and take lunch on a sunny rock, we’ve heard a couple reports of a trail closure ahead, but no specifics. There’s a ranger station somewhere at Grey, but honestly we’re ready to get back to hiking and out of this bustling village. (Grey is a hike-in location but has a full service lodge/hostel and looks like it could easily hold 100 tents or more.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re now in an area of the park that burned just a couple years ago in a fire reportedly started by someone burning toilet paper. With all the shade gone, the summer sun is intense. The trail is now just a constant stream of people; in the couple hours it takes to hike from Grey to Paine Grande, there’s probably less than 10 minutes total with no other groups in sight. Even so, the vistas are stunning. And meeting people on the trail is a bit interesting. Hikers hail from all around the world; we hear lots of French, Spanish, and German, but also Chinese, Nordic Languages, and others among all flavors of English accents. While in all likelihood English is the more common shared language, most groups acknowledge each other with a simple ¡Hola!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we arrive at Paine Grande, we meet a ranger at the trail junction where we’ll head tomorrow. It’s closed. Luckily the ranger spot-on for this job: he’s totally chill, and also encourages us to just chill out, not worry about reservations, and just go with the flow; the park is amazing even if it’s not what you planned. After gathering a couple more details, we decide that today’s travel isn’t over just yet and race to catch the catamaran docked a couple hundred yards down the shore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-11-cat-pano.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View from the Catamaran&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re a bit baffled, trying to figure out what happens next: where can we get to for the night? Should we have just stayed and caught a possible ferry around the outage? &lt;em&gt;Do we have enough cash?&lt;/em&gt; I try to take the ranger’s advice, and at least for now, it’s easy let my mind wander as I gawk at the incredible view of Cuernos as we speed across the lake. At Pudeto it’s a bit more stressful. We wait on the porch of a cafe which helps break the constant wind, but it’s still cold. Some backpackers are able to hitch rides, but vehicles are few and far between, most already hired private tours understandably not willing to take backpackers. We’re also just not that outgoing and figure we’ll wait for a bus towards Laguna Amarga / Torres Central. Of course, the schedules aren’t super clear - it could be 4 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never taken a boat and bus ride in the middle of a backpacking trip, but there’s a first time for everything. As the catamaran pulls up to Pudeto after making another round trip, buses from every company rumble in. We’re happy to see them. This run wasn’t listed on our published schedule. An hour or so later, we’re enjoying dinner in the camping zone at Torres Central.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-december-2016&quot;&gt;6 December 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The landscape to the west out of Torres Central is again unique, the rocky soil mostly bare and grassy which affords views up towards Cuernos as well as sweeping vistas to the south. A young canadian couple out for a trail run pass us; we see them pause for a selfie on the next ridge before they continue on out of sight. The morning is surprisingly calm, but it is only a matter of time before the trickle of hikers headed towards us becomes a more constant train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-12-cuernos.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cuernos del Paine rising above Nordenskjöld Lake&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuernos del Paine is a beautiful formation, two enormous veins of golden granite capped with red/brown spires, with a third, miniature peak set in front. I’m glad we got the chance to see it from the catamaran and bus yesterday; today’s view is awe-inspiring but a significantly different angle, we’re right beneath the rock. After passing through the bustling Cuernos camp and lodge, the trail quiets down; with the bridge out there won’t have been many people at Italiano last night. It’s slow going on a trail surface of softball sized rocks by the lake; we note swimming opportunities for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francés camping zone is sheltered by forest at the base of Valle Francés. We chat with the ranger, set up camp, and give our feet a break. Our day isn’t quite over: today is our chance to venture to the lookouts above camp. We load a single pack with warmth and snacks and start uphill. It’s not too long before the Canadians from this morning pass us headed down; they’ll make it back to Torres Central before dark. We hear mini-avalanches as chunks of ice fall from glaciers and soon enough are rewarded by a view to the glacier from a bald patch. Continuing further up the trail jumps in and out of braided drainages, some forested and wet, others bare and rocky, the result of rockslides and avalances past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spend almost an hour at Británico. No pictures can do this place justice, in part because the dancing clouds are even more stunning than the granite which surrounds, rising from every direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-13-frances.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fog rolls through Valle Francés from the Británico lookout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-december-2016&quot;&gt;7 December 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really looking forward to today’s hike - it’s mostly just retracing our steps from yesterday. A quick dip in the lake comes just an hour out of camp (would have been more appreciated later in the day?), but it’s still a great refresher. Continuing on, I catch a few views and features that we missed on the way in, but it’s generally predictable and still as crowded as ever. We watch baffled as a group of 25 (!) people who clearly aren’t used to backpacking take a major off-trail detour through scrub on the next ridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re afforded our only solitude of the day as we push up a meadow bypassing the lodge at Torres Central. It’s the last full day and while our packs have lightened up, our legs are tired. We’re anticipating seeing the Torres peak out as we round the corner into valle ascensio, but end up making it all the way to the main trail before we finally pause and refuel. The trail here is more accurately described as a highway - backpackers at every stage of their trip, dayhikers, and even horses fill the way up the valley. At Chileno tents occupy wooden platforms built into the steep valley walls and the park’s namesake formation finally shows itself again. After another hour of jockeying with other trail users (and not really paying much attention to the surrounding forest, to be honest), the forest opens up at the bottom of a rockslide and we follow rocks with day-glo yellow tape into camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-december-2016&quot;&gt;8 December 2016&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My watch alarm goes off at 4am. It’s dark outside, but once I get my bearings it’s obvious we aren’t the only ones awake. The reflective markers make trail-finding surprisingly easy; every time I’m the least bit confused, scanning with my headlamp quickly reveals a new marker. Technically hiking at dark is prohibited by park rules so the reflective hits are an unexpected touch. Above the trees I no longer need a light at all and it’s peaceful to hike in the dark with the lights of other groups seeking the sunrise bouncing around up and down the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Torres is better in person that the photos which make all kinds of weird tricks for scale, but my first impression is that I’d still take Britanico or John Gardner Pass over this view. It doesn’t help that it’s cold and windy, and it doesn’t look like we’re going to experience the storied golden glow of Torres at sunrise - low clouds move quickly but show no signs of breaking up. After an hour or so of watching condors cruise among the spires and pointing out increasingly intricate irregularities in the rock faces, we ask another group to snap a couple photos and head downhill with no regrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/chile-14-torres.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Torres del Paine on a foggy morning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back at Chileno blue sky begins to show itself and light up the towers. We snap a few photos, but to be honest it’s just like yesterday afternoon’s approach. After just another hour flying downhill we’re back at the Torres Central lodge with mixed feelings. An amazing trip with an anti-climactic ending, but more than enough memories. A modern adventure booking office and cafe provides shade, impressively clean washrooms, and a place for us to relax and reflect while waiting for the bus back to Puerto Natales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our stop at Puerto Natales is unfortunately limited to the bus station. I would have liked to pick up more mixed dried fruit and nuts, but we’ve purchased tickets on to Punta Arenas and town is a 15 minute walk from the bus station. The bus seats aren’t great for sleeping, but it doesn’t matter. I nod in and out of consciousness, catching occasional glimpses across the desolate southern chilean prairie until we finally pull in. After an adventure to the wrong side of town (thanks to a mis-keyed tourist buereau / hostel association map) we check in, drop our packs, and head out for a new adventure: post-trail dinner and beer! I’m still not sure of my feelings on the pizzas we consumed from &lt;a href=&quot;http://dinospizza.cl/&quot;&gt;Dino’s Pizza&lt;/a&gt;, but if anything it was a fitting close to our Torres del Paine adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to still have a couple days in Chile - the backpacking was amazing, but I’m excited to see what else Punta Arenas and Santiago have to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be continued…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/travel/2016/12/15/chile.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/travel/2016/12/15/chile.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Lost Time Orienteering</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;I volunteer with the Cascade Orienteering Club results team, managing software and hardware that verifies course completion and calculates results. As soon as I started in this position, I noticed opportunities to simplify both pre- and post-meet tasks. Working off and on over about a year, I developed a web tool that simplifies the job. Fifteen minute tasks can now be completed in seconds, without worry of error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/LostTimeHeader2.png&quot; alt=&quot;LostTimeOrienteering header&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the tasks are data transformation, some are more complex calculations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Load registration information from a couple sources into the meet management software.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assign point values to finishers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Format results for posting to the CascadeOC website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calculate team results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calculate series standings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the tool is developed for CascadeOC, the architecture is such that any club may be able to leverage the tool for similar tasks with a little bit of additional configuration work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;technical-notes&quot;&gt;Technical Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python is my go-to language, and I’ve now built a number of sites using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://flask.pocoo.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; web development micro-framework. I’m hooked up to a SQLite database, which handles the (tiny) load with no issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major shout-out to &lt;a href=&quot;https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/commandline/wsl/about&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Windows Subsystem for Linux (aka Bash/Ubuntu on Windows)&lt;/a&gt;. I’m able to develop on my PC without messing around with VMs or a linux partition, and I get an accurate representation of how the code will run on my web host’s linux box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can view and make your own fork of the code on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ercjns/LostTime&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;; pull requests welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2016/11/06/lost-time-orienteering.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2016/11/06/lost-time-orienteering.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Pizza Delivery</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;My uncle runs a couple of pizza delivery stores in the Greenville, SC area. His web host and site template provider functionally disappeared in June 2016. I was able to recover most of his site content from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;wayback machine&lt;/a&gt;, but with the editing software gone in the wind, he was unable to make updates. This was as good a catalyst as any to have his site re-built from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I’ve built basic websites previously, I had never taken a project where I needed to hand over full control to a less technical person at the end of development. I brushed up on WordPress and spent some time learning about his business before building out his new site. Ultimately we ended up with something I’m proud of and something that my uncle can update himself except in extreme cases, so I’m quite happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and the pizza is good too! If you’re in the area, grab some grub from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wedgysonline.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wedgy’s Pizza Delivery&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/Wedgys.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wedgy's Pizza Delivery&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2016/09/15/pizza-delivery.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2016/09/15/pizza-delivery.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Orienteering Live Results</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Orienteering is map and compass navigation racing. Here in Puget Sound, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cascadeoc.org&quot;&gt;Cascade Orienteering Club&lt;/a&gt; hosts meets all year, some attended by more than four hundred competitors. Orienteering is an anti-climactic sport: competitors start individually in 2 minute intervals, race their course (through the woods and out of sight), and return to the finish. Even though this is a race for the fastest time, there is never a head-to-head race to the finish. Also, because every course is different, it can be hard to judge an individual’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live results provide coaches and competitors with faster feedback about the race. With this information on-site, individuals and teams can de-brief while still present in the environment, which likely leads to easier recognition of possible corrections and faster improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/WiFi-phone-home.png&quot; alt=&quot;WiFi Results Home Page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;system-design&quot;&gt;System Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because many event sites have limited or no cell phone coverage, the entire system is designed around a web server broadcasting pages over a local WiFi network. As competitors finish the course, event software records information from their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=orienteering+electronic+punching&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;e-punch&lt;/a&gt; (rfid-like tracking device) and compiles results. The event software is able to export preliminary results at set time intervals, which is the input data for the public live results system. The exported file is routed to a Raspberry Pi which processes it and builds a database each time a new file is received. Some local DNS tricks on a WiFi router and a web server running on the Pi allow anyone on site to connect to a public WiFi network and view the current results. Running this system on the Pi rather than directly on the event laptop helps with modularity and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;technical-details&quot;&gt;Technical Details&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the code (and the readme) on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ercjns/O-coc-wifiscoring&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current server is built on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://flask.pocoo.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; micro-framework for Python and uses a SQLite database. It all runs on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/products/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi 2&lt;/a&gt;. The event software can export the preliminary results file (an .xml file) directly to a folder on the Pi thanks to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samba.org/samba/what_is_samba.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;samba&lt;/a&gt; share. On the Pi, a simple script monitors this directory for changes. When a new file is detected, the script sends the file to the server (another process on the Pi) via HTTP POST request. The server reads the xml and loads the data to the database, recalculating points for individuals and teams. When a user connects to the local WiFi network and requests a page, the Pi dynamically builds and serves the appropriate html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;variations&quot;&gt;Variations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At three events in February and March 2016, this system was successfully deployed (in areas with cell coverage) such that results were available both via an a internet-facing web server and via the local WiFi. This was trivial: a duplicate web-facing server was running on Heroku, and the script on the Pi was altered to POST each new results xml file to both the localhost and the internet server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At three events in Winter 2015-2016, this system captured and displayed information from the check or start control in real time, with the help of some additional hardware and integration of the socketIO library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous event software didn’t have periodic export functionality, so a solution was developed to intercept data as it was sent to the results ticket printer. This worked but was undesirable as the system existed within the critical path for the event. This solution was abandoned when the club independently decided to switch to different event software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous iterations of this project used &lt;a href=&quot;http://expressjs.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Express&lt;/a&gt; on node.js as the backbone. The project switched to python due to more stable support for python on the Pi and other potential hardware targets which were being investigated.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2015/10/10/orienteering-live-results.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2015/10/10/orienteering-live-results.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
