<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Eric Jones</title>
		<description>Eric Jones builds software, travels by bicycle, and is only slightly obsessed with maps.</description>
		<link>http://www.ercjns.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://www.ercjns.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>A New Routine (January 2018)</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Today looks like any other day from the past few weeks: grey clouds blanket the treetops, and the Seattle rain makes no sound yet I can see the drops bouncing off the table outside. But today is different. Today is February. The first month of the year has come and gone. It’s time for a check-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started a new job in January: I’m now working as a math (and sometimes science) teacher at a tutoring center in Redmond. It is good to have work again, and having a schedule that holds me accountable means I generally use my remaining time a bit more productively than I did previously. (I miss you, twitch chat friends!) Of course, having a job isn’t the only thing in life - I set out some goals in my year-in-review post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More writing and reflecting&lt;/strong&gt;: I’ve taken weekly time to jot down notes, but I’m not doing this well enough that it is bringing change. Writing regularly does feels good, so I’m excited to continue improving here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Say yes to more / get out more&lt;/strong&gt;: Based on the above, it’s not surprising that I have no meaningful change to report here. Time to focus on this more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look a bit more towards the long term&lt;/strong&gt;: Taking a job means this is both going well (yay positive cash flow!), and that I really need to be careful to continue working at it or I’ll end up in the same place I was when I quit my previous job without a plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;teaching&quot;&gt;Teaching&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To all my teachers and mentors from pre-school through college and beyond, and to all who teach and work with children now: Thank you. Education is so important, and at least here in the US we generally don’t give teachers the support, recognition, or credit they deserve. I’ve always believed this, but it’s so much more real after spending some time on the other side of the desk these past few weeks. My typical tutoring schedule is Monday through Friday evenings, and I generally work with high school students. Last week my Friday shift got cancelled (end of finals week) and I filled in for a Saturday shift at another location. New location, new students, and - surprise to me - nearly all elementary school kids. It was &lt;em&gt;such&lt;/em&gt; a different challenge, and honestly one that I wasn’t prepared for. I’ll need to come up with some ideas for next time I take that shift. That experience is also where &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ercjns/status/957432750306308096&quot;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt; came from, though I shouldn’t have needed to be prompted. After three weeks on the job I’m pretty comfortable with the 3:1 teaching ratio and the record-keeping, and I even feel like I’ve built a relationship with a few of my students. That said, there’s still a lot for me to learn and improve. Without a doubt, this job is a challenge. I’m not totally sold on it being interesting or exciting work, but spending my time on something that is challenging and rewarding is miles ahead of how I felt prior to leaving my previous job, so I’m taking that as a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;birthdays&quot;&gt;Birthdays&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, February 1st, is my internet birthday. It’s the date I use for my birthday on websites that don’t need to know my real birthday, which is most. It’s also not all that far off from my real birthday, and I’ve been thinking that I’d like to actually celebrate this year. The past few years, I’ve generally just sheepishly eaten the giant cookie my mom has sent (Thanks mom!) over the course of a few days and subsequently felt bad that I didn’t share it with more people (and avoid a minor stomach ache). This seems like as good an excuse as any to make some demonstrable progress on goal #2: get out more. Maybe I’ll find a spot for dinner and drinks with a few friends. My birthday only happens once a year - might as well make something good out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bicycling&quot;&gt;Bicycling&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other side effect of getting back into “employed” status is that I ride my bike at least five days a week now. (My bicycle is my commuter vehicle, rain or shine.) Getting to work is about four miles each way, nearly entirely flat, half on paved trails, and the rest on roads with bike lanes. This is a very comfortable commute, although the reactions from my co-workers would make you think otherwise. More people should bike. Anyways, riding home at night is especially refreshing, and brings me back to when I would occasionally set out from Olin on weeknight rides through the Boston suburbs. Bicycling on dark and quiet suburban streets is so relaxing - the whirr of my chain is a comforting undertone to the calm of the night, only broken by passing cars few and far between. It’s a perfect way to wind down after a stressful shift, and getting my legs moving is pretty important after sitting for six hours straight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s still raining. It’s still cold and windy. But the earth is orbiting the sun at 30km/s, so there must be something new to appreciate in the world around you all the time. It might take some work, but you can find it. Good luck out there, friends.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/life/2018/02/01/a-new-routine-january-2018.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/life/2018/02/01/a-new-routine-january-2018.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Looking Forward and Back</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to 2018. You made it! Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many, December 31 marks an end, and January 1 a new beginning. Sure, a date is a bit arbitrary in the grand scheme of things, but the turning of the year is as good a reminder as any that it is important to take time to reflect on the past in order to make the most of the future. There is a lot that happened in 2017. 365 days. 8760 hours. Time for a slightly closer look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-year-in-review&quot;&gt;A year in review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply, here’s a happy memory or accomplishment from each month of my 2017. Some are big events, some just small encounters that I’m glad I came across. Remember that everything you accomplish or enjoy - no matter the size - is important because it makes you who you are, and no one can take that from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;January&lt;/em&gt; - I enjoyed some interesting games of “not jenga” with friends at Monday Night Dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;February&lt;/em&gt; - I went to Portland for a weekend where I ate donuts and visited with friends from college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;March&lt;/em&gt; - I got to catch up with a bunch of high school friends I hadn’t seen in almost a decade at a wedding back home in Alpharetta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;April&lt;/em&gt; - I marched in the Seattle March for Science. There were a lot of very punny signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;May&lt;/em&gt; - I rode my bicycle on Seattle freeways in the 2nd (hopefully annual) Emerald City Bike Ride. I made a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LDwdlvEPffs&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; about it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;June&lt;/em&gt; - I went on a four day trip to a bunch of orienteering events in central and eastern Washington. I made another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3sHMjpoDP-A&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;July&lt;/em&gt; - My housemates and I hosted an Olin College summer party for about 50 alumni, current students, incoming students, and families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;August&lt;/em&gt; - I &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ercjns/status/899671708847570951&quot;&gt;watched&lt;/a&gt; the Solar Eclipse with a pinhole viewer from my kayak in the middle of Lake Sammamish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;September&lt;/em&gt; - I won the Fremont Street Scramble on a beautiful fall morning. I also raced in an amazing sprint orienteering tournament and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/09/10/sart.html&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;October&lt;/em&gt; - I went hiking with a friend at Cutthroat Pass in the North Cascades on a beautiful bluebird day after early season snow. We found the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ercjns/status/917269274653351937&quot;&gt;Larch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;November&lt;/em&gt; - I met some extended family in Nashville for Thanksgiving and got to see some cousins I hadn’t seen in a few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;December&lt;/em&gt; - I made updates to an orienteering map of a large local park, then designed and set courses for an event attended by over 400 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you too can take a minute to think about your past year and find that you’ve done so much!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-back&quot;&gt;Looking back&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, who you are is shaped by much more than a few accomplishments. There are struggles and challenges, new and uncomfortable situations, plans that go awry, spontaneous activities, and the nondescript monotony of whatever day to day life actually is. With so many waking hours in a year, it is a fools errand to ask for it to all be analysed and improved, but that doesn’t mean there is zero opportunity. Here’s a couple ideas of things I’d like to change:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wasn’t focused on long-term personal goals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I let too many decisions make themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I rarely strayed outside my comfort zone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the difficult part. It’s often easier to identify opportunities for change than to actually make those changes. I don’t yet know the strategies I’ll use to tackle the specific ideas mentioned above, but that doesn’t mean I can let this fall flat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get started, I have a straightforward resolution for 2018: &lt;strong&gt;spend more time writing and reflecting&lt;/strong&gt;. On teams in the workplace and at school I’ve always advocated for the value of retrospectives, yet I don’t use that strategy in my personal life. Time for that to change. I’ve already set up a weekly timebox, and I’m going to use the first couple weeks to discover the right questions to be asking and answering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I’m going to work on pressuring myself to say yes to more things. I definitely need my alone time, but I also want to get out more, try more new things, and spend more time with friends, both old and new. How will I actually achieve this? Checking in on my results during weekly journaling seems like a great way to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next twelve months will give you and me yet another year of experience in living, in becoming ourselves. As with every new adventure, there will be mistakes, but that’s ok. Mistakes (especially big ones!) can often be the best way to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to see what 2018 brings and who I become. I hope you too grow through many new adventures. Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/life/2018/01/01/looking-forward-and-back.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/life/2018/01/01/looking-forward-and-back.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Seattle Adventure Running Tournament</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend I raced in the 2017 edition of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sart.cascadeoc.org&quot;&gt;Seattle Adventure Running Tournament&lt;/a&gt; (SART), a set of six sprint orienteering races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main defining feature of SART is the bracket: rather than earning points for placement, totalling elapsed time, or some other method of scoring individual races, competitors are split into heats of five and race to move up and down the bracket. And unlike typical orienteering races where competitors are started at intervals in order to discourage following, SART heats start with all five people at once. It’s both exhilarating and terrifying, and I love it. Before I share my thoughts, a huge thank you to Patrick, SART Event Director, and the volunteer team. There is an incomprehensible amount of work that goes into this event and it has gone off without major issues every year. With that said, let’s get off to the races!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/seattleadventurerunning/2017_Bracket_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/sart17-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;SART Bracket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;round-0-life-comes-at-you-fast&quot;&gt;Round 0: Life comes at you fast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/seattleadventurerunning/2017_SART_0.pdf&quot;&gt;College Place Schools&lt;/a&gt; | Results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cascadeoc.org/result/sart-2017-time-trial-college-place-middle/&quot;&gt;Cascade&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://obasen.orientering.se/winsplits/online/en/default.asp?page=table&amp;amp;databaseId=51282&amp;amp;categoryId=0&quot;&gt;Winsplits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick and flat mile long jaunt around an elementary and middle school campus in light rain. (Our first rain in months?) Fences and buildings with overhangs presented a good opportunity to get into the urban sprint orienteering mindset, though overall this was a very simple map with few actual traps. The dense grid of small buildings created plenty of corners to duck around, which helped this race feel less like a simple following exercise. (Individuals started every 30s for this race.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt pretty good when I finished, but certainly felt like I could have gone faster. Apparently that wasn’t necessary as I earned the 4th place seed. Because of the balanced bracket, I consider the time trial to be one of the more important races. With my high seed, I should be able to relax for the next two races and save my legs for when it really matters: squeezing into the top 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-design-2-to-3&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (design): 2 to 3&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented with many similar options through the buildings and to the inside corner of a fence (check your control descriptions!), I chose quickly, but had a slight bobble when I ran past the first building in a blur and didn’t count it off in my head. At 1:4000 scale, life comes at you fast!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;round-1-dont-trust-the-top-seed&quot;&gt;Round 1: Don’t trust the top seed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/seattleadventurerunning/2017_SART_1.pdf&quot;&gt;Lynndale Park&lt;/a&gt; | Results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cascadeoc.org/result/sart-2017-round-1-lynndale-park/&quot;&gt;Cascade&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://obasen.orientering.se/winsplits/online/en/default.asp?page=table&amp;amp;databaseId=51283&amp;amp;categoryId=0&quot;&gt;Winsplits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hilliest round of the tournament in a forested park with a maze of trails and ravines. Never underestimate the challenge of a local park; making the correct lefts and rights on social trails in quick succession at sprint speed isn’t always easy, as I learned on the way from 1 to 2. Tight corners and quick changes in terrain types also created a challenge exiting number 10, where paths lead in every direction. After the quick u-turns necessary to get into and out of the control, I chose the wrong path on the way out. Don’t forget to use your compass!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, because the high seeds are spread out across the bracket, I didn’t have any real pressure after dropping the rest of my heat by control 4 or 5. While this was always going to be a pretty relaxed race for me, that’s not true for everyone. This race splits the field into top 40 and bottom 40, so if your goal is to be above &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; bubble, this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; most important race of the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-design--experience-start-to-1&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (design &amp;amp; experience): Start to 1&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first leg was relatively long, but required an almost immediate decision after flipping the map. In the first heat (which included seeds 1, 32, 33, 64, 65), everyone looked on as four went left while only a junior went right. From then on, nearly everyone went left and checked the map on the way for the next decision (myself included). Turns out we were all wrong, and the junior was correct. Don’t trust the top seed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;round-2-it-wont-be-easy-after-this&quot;&gt;Round 2: It won’t be easy after this&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/seattleadventurerunning/2017_SART_2.pdf&quot;&gt;Edmonds Community College&lt;/a&gt; | Results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cascadeoc.org/result/sart-2017-round-2-edmonds-community-college/&quot;&gt;Cascade&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://obasen.orientering.se/winsplits/online/en/default.asp?page=table&amp;amp;databaseId=51284&amp;amp;categoryId=0&quot;&gt;Winsplits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is an entirely new map, it ran just like the other seattle area community college maps Patrick has made, which is to say very fast, but requiring some careful concentration. All the community colleges seem to have similar layouts with a small core of about 10 oddly shaped buildings and plazas, surrounded by huge parking lots and a few other features. This often makes for great courses, with route choices in and out of the campus core that can penalize mistakes by a good 5 to 10 seconds on a 60 second leg. The characteristically Seattle overcast skies were a much appreciated feature for my 3:12pm start time - and a major change from the high 80s, sun, and haze/smoke we’ve had the past few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having moved up, I was challenged a bit more out of the starting blocks this round with Scott and Christophe punching only a couple seconds behind me at 2, but both went down the stairs and lost about 10 seconds on the way to 3. My correct route choice under pressure was a huge confidence boost, and with a couple hedges now between me and them, I had first locked in save a terrible mistake. The race wasn’t over for the rest of my heat though: all four in the train behind me battled it out all the way to number 15 before starting to separate. That’s the kind of high stakes racing I love about SART, and I suspect I’ll get it in the next round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-design-15-to-16&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (design): 15 to 16&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A deceptively simple leg that isn’t so simple at the end of a race. I took what I believe is the best route, staying right on the path along the fence, then south of the building and into the control. Left and through the parking lot looks great until you realize you must approach the control from the south corner of the building, at which point the zig-zag through the parking lot hurts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;round-3-night-train&quot;&gt;Round 3: Night Train&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/seattleadventurerunning/2017_SART_3.pdf&quot;&gt;Lynnwood Golf Course&lt;/a&gt; | Results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cascadeoc.org/result/sart-2017-round-3-lynnwood-golf-course/&quot;&gt;Cascade&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://obasen.orientering.se/winsplits/online/en/default.asp?page=table&amp;amp;databaseId=51289&amp;amp;categoryId=0&quot;&gt;Winsplits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s dark. It’s a brand new map. And not just that, it’s a map unlike one I’ve ever run on: a golf course. Oh, and this is the race that will separate the top 10 from those who finish the weekend ranking 11 to 20. This is my bubble race, I’m not a top 5 contender in this field. No pressure. Maybe this will take the nerves off:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/8BVgeEHfuG0?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graeme took the lead out of the blocks and all five of us punched 1 together. And 2. And 3. And 4. When I say together, I mean it - I saw Eric B’s punch in the control before mine and Tori was waiting in the same way for me. I actually didn’t have any idea where Ott was, but I had to assume he was right behind Tori (he was about 10s back at number 4). I was getting suspicious at this point - the pace felt a bit slow for this elite crew, but we were all still getting familiar with matching the map to the (dark, shadowy) terrain. I was tentatively happy to let Graeme and Eric duke it out a few seconds ahead of me but in the back of my mind I knew that a third place finish is no guarantee of moving up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pace accelerated noticeably around 5 or 6, now that we were all more confident with the map. With me still right on Eric’s back, I suspect Graeme and Eric had no idea how big our train was at that point, but both exploded out of 8, making the expected move to try to shake off followers on the long leg to the south end of the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric B punched first at 9, but to my amazement I was still only a few seconds back. Close third is an extremely fun place to race from: with two competitors trying slight variations on routes ahead of me, all it takes is a small mistake from either for me to swoop in and grab second. And I can stay tight because from third I have the best angle to react to whoever ahead of me pinpoints the control location. That said, third is not first, and a mistake may also be my only opportunity. It can be tough to pass on short, straight legs due to the slight pause as each person punches creating an extra half-second of separation even if you’re at the control at the same time. It’s also a risk to jump ahead too early with this crew - navigating at the front takes significantly more mental work than following, and I’m sure that whoever is behind me will be happy to take advantage of any mistakes I might make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opportunity presents itself at the next control: Graeme overshot 10 by a few steps and I managed to punch second, helped in by the red flash and audible beep of the control box. Time to keep my head in the game, there’s heavy breathing right behind me again. At 12 I go left around a thicket in order to have a smooth exit and beat Eric B to the flag by a step. I’m in first!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also out of breath and there’s a US National team member and a very fast Canadian chasing me down this par 3 in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m perfect to 13, but bobble 14 and have lost the couple steps of separation I had created. I punch 15 in second and at 16 I’m back in third. G splits left to 17 while I stick with E, deciding that I’d rather not pass through the deep dark forest. It turns out it’s about a tossup. We pick up Julia from the previous heat, and she does well to stick with us for the last couple legs to the finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About three minutes later Will casually walks the last 10m to the finish, his heat mates not yet in sight. “Some of us had to work for this, ya know!” quips Graeme. Once we confirm those of us from the night train all have faster times than Will (who won the heat we’re matched with), I know I’m through to the top 10. What a way to finish the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-design-1-to-2&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (design): 1 to 2&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start to 1 might downplay the complexities of this map, but on 1 to 2 they slap you in the face. Exit the right direction with a compass (it’s night, so good luck just looking for that green across the way), slip between the green and the sand, across the cart path, pop through the trees and … well, at this point I honestly have no idea if I’m right or left of the line. After a wide open easy first leg, this was an awesome reset of expectations for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-experience-11-to-12-to-13&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (experience): 11 to 12 to 13&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the rush of racing head to head, and it doesn’t get better than slipping into the lead and having people chasing you down while you’re all making decisions about where to go. I didn’t get enough of this in the earlier rounds, so I’m glad I was able to lead this one for a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;round-4-forgot-to-carry-sandbags&quot;&gt;Round 4: Forgot to carry sandbags&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/seattleadventurerunning/2017_SART_4.pdf&quot;&gt;South Seattle College&lt;/a&gt; | Results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cascadeoc.org/result/sart-2017-round-4-south-seattle-college/&quot;&gt;Cascade&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://obasen.orientering.se/winsplits/online/en/default.asp?page=table&amp;amp;databaseId=51334&amp;amp;categoryId=0&quot;&gt;Winsplits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New day, new venue, new map. Tired, nervous, and sore legs. Realistically, I’m not moving up and should save everything for round five, but where’s the fun in that? Flipping the map I was surprised to find a chunk of medium green, trails, and contours filling the middle third of the page. Nothing too tricky, but anything unexpected is an added challenge. I felt like this round ended up as more of a run than an orienteering race as there were only a few route choices to make, but I’m sure a lot of that was to save the more complex parts of the map for the final.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already in fifth by number 2, but kept visual contact with the pack through about 10. Mistakes happen, but at this point I really should have slowed up to save for the final. My brain had other ideas, because as my pack moved further and further away, I saw they had picked up and overtaken Siri from the previous heat. Now I have an achievable goal for this round: could I catch up to her? (This, of course, is dumb strategy - unless there are a comedy of mistakes from the leaders, I’m going to be racing Siri head to head in the final round no matter my time here.) Oh well. I keep the gas on and finally pass in the sprint to the finish. To the 6th place final we go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-design-6-to-7&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (design): 6 to 7&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the race I completely missed that there was a choice here. That’s the gotcha of just following the back of a pack. Everyone ahead of me went over the wall and up through tall grass, and I begrudgingly followed, oblivious to the fact that I could have taken a more gradual climb on much better footing and a very similar distance traveled by going left and up the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-experience-start-to-1&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (experience): start to 1&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An entirely unexpected, long-ish forest trails leg to start the round. Graeme, Will, and Eric B all went right ahead of me, while I tentatively made the decision to go left, followed by David. We popped out a few steps ahead, almost getting run over by the pack flying downhill on a straight trail. (I was passed on the way up the hill to 1, but still a fun start!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;round-5-so-close-yet-so-far&quot;&gt;Round 5: So close, yet so far…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/seattleadventurerunning/2017_SART_5.pdf&quot;&gt;South Seattle College&lt;/a&gt; | Results: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cascadeoc.org/result/sart-2017-round-5-champs-south-seattle-college/&quot;&gt;Cascade&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://obasen.orientering.se/winsplits/online/en/show_event.asp?id=51335&quot;&gt;Winsplits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bracket has done its job admirably: my heat is Graeme, Peteris, David, Siri, and myself, which on paper should be my tightest race all weekend. It’s a bit of a stretch but certainly possible for me to beat all of these people. It’s also easily possible for each and every one of them to beat me. If all goes well, I won’t know the answer until about 15 minutes after Kathy says “Go!” and we’re all sprinting to the finish together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Round 5 is forked, meaning that we each get variations of the same course. At SART, this is done by creating loops of controls that runners take in a different order from each other. At the first hub control, some start with loop A, others with loop B. At a second hub, repeat this idea with different pairings, creating four different courses for the five runners. (In previous years there have been three loops at the first hub, allowing for five totally different courses, but also leaving one runner solo. I’m curious to know why this wasn’t included this year - it’s possible that the map just couldn’t handle it, but also possible that Patrick decided the solo runner had an unfair disadvantage.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Get ready!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few clouds float in an otherwise clear blue sky, an occasional breeze provides relief from the warm sun. My heart is racing. I lean forward, right hand gripping the watch on my left wrist, the compass on my left thumb now hidden from view so it’s face up on the map I’m about to flip. On my right wrist are the 29 control descriptions. I’ve discerned that the first hub is number 1, I have a loop of three, then a loop of four, and then a few more controls before more loops. While I’m with the train to 1, I need to find 2 and 6 on my map so I have a better shot at picking the correct line (of six options) out of the first hub. Every second counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Go!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a brush of familiarity, Graeme and I are paired for the first loop, and I stick right on his tail. Back at the hub I see Siri, but everything else is a blur, with people from many heats here now. I’m with Graeme again for loop two at the fist hub, and lose a second questioning this fact. (Only after the race did I put it together that with only two loops, I’ll race with the same people until we complete the hub.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Down the corridor to 11, I’m in second behind Graeme, but I have no idea what’s happening behind me. No time to look. I see Graeme run past 13 and I punch first, but to my surprise see both Grameme and Siri heading towards me when I look up on my way out. How did I not notice Siri get ahead?! (I’ll find out after the race she went North around the building to 13 while Graeme and I went East/South.) I make a couple bobbles into the parking lot on the way to 14, and after punching, get my first view that yes, &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; is still bunched up. This next hub is going to be a doozy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graeme passes me on the way into the gardens, and Peteris is right on my tail. I stumble my way to 16 in this maze, and find it’s Peteris who is now right behind me. I haven’t planned the next leg. I mistakenly go too far west and punch after Peteris at 17 and 18. Back at the hub no one else is in sight. I lose Peteris on the way to 20, but after a confident route choice returning the way I had come, am surprised to punch just ahead at 21. Back at a hub for the last time, it’s sill anyone’s race. Graeme (who did this set of loops opposite me) and I punch together, with David and Peteris only a few steps behind. I don’t see Siri, but have to believe she’s still a threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the rest of the course is light on navigation, and at this point I’m already on my last legs. Out of the gardens we all head right and I’ve dropped back to fourth on shaky legs as we cross the sunny field towards construction fences. I gain a few steps taking the road between new and old construction, but lose that gain and more going left around the building rather than through the courtyard to 23. I’m trying to push, but it just isn’t there. At 25 I bobble my punch and get discouraged, allowing a 3 second gap to expand to 5. Only a mispunch or a major mistake will change the finish order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exiting 28, the crowd is in view, as is Graeme leading our heat to 29 and the finish. We’re tight, but not tight enough that a last second burst of speed can change anything. We each turn it up for a final push: Graeme gains another two seconds over Peteris, and David makes up one of those while the now six second gap between David and I remains unchanged. Just past the finish, we all flop, completely winded. I was only 15 seconds behind Graeme. So close, yet so far. I manage to sit up and high-five Siri after she comes in just 25 seconds behind me, a single mistake in the gardens accounting for nearly all of that gap. A couple bobbles and the smallest bit of running speed at the end of a long weekend of racing is all that separates 6th from 10th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-design-the-garden-loops&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (design): the garden loops&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a great technical challenge, and navigating fast was tricky! I had the west loop of three before the east loop of two, and boy were there just so many options to every single control. In sprints, pick a route quickly and execute well is typically my strategy, and that generally held here: good execution on a non optimal route didn’t lose much time. But that wasn’t without exceptions - there were some trails with wandering, roundabout paths that could be punishing, making me pause more than I wanted to in this high stakes race! I also really appreciated that while the map looks to be a possibly confusing mix of out-of-bounds and in-bounds terrain, the out-of-bounds areas were generally quite obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;favorite-leg-experience-10-to-11&quot;&gt;Favorite Leg (experience): 10 to 11&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was so fun - a long straight corridor after completing the first hub giving everyone a chance to see where they stand. Maybe not the most interesting orienteering, but in a head to head heat, this was thrilling. I was in 2nd and chose to not look back, but if I had I would have seen Siri, David, and Peteris biting at my heels!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-summary-mayhem&quot;&gt;In Summary: Mayhem!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m proud of my 9th place finish, a repeat placement from last year in a different but equally challenging field. And I felt like I earned every bit of it this year, not squeezing in somewhere due to a bracket pairing, mispunch, or dq. Overall in the field, I placed 9th in Round 1, 10th in Round 2, 4th in Round 3, 9th in Round 4, and 8th in Round 5. I got to experience the thrill of leading a pack as well as the heartbreak of trailing with no way to move up. I got to jostle for position in a crazy race at night against competitors known internationally. I ate a lot of cookies and gummy bears. It was a great weekend. See you next year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/sart17-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SART Maps and bib&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/09/10/sart.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/09/10/sart.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Bikes on the Freeway!</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend I rode in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cascade.org/rides-major-rides/emerald-bike-ride&quot;&gt;Emerald Bike Ride&lt;/a&gt; hosted by Cascade Bicycle Club. This was the ride’s second year, and it was an amazing route that won’t ever be exactly duplicated. Though it didn’t sell out (as the inaugural ride did), the freeways (we rode on closed portions of I-5, WA-520, and I-90) were still jammed with bikes, including riders of all ages and a good number of unicycles on the 25 mile loop. I take every chance I get to ride or run on shutdown freeways. Experiencing the massive infrastructure while not inside a car gives great perspective for how much space freeways use. Big thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cascade.org&quot;&gt;Cascade&lt;/a&gt; for continuing to organize this ride and to WSDOT and the cities for allowing it to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I’ve been looking for a good chance to try my hand at producing some video as a side project, and this turned out to be a great opportunity. I learned a lot of new tools, spent a lot of time fighting myself (and my editing software), and ultimately ended up with something I’m pretty happy with given it’s my first try. I hope you enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LDwdlvEPffs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/05/29/bikes-on-the-freeway.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/05/29/bikes-on-the-freeway.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Creating Being Lost</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve written before about the web development work I do to help Cascade Orienteering Club put on events. I enjoy that behind the scenes work, making the jobs of event volunteers a little easier. From time to time, I also take a slightly more visible role in making orienteering meets happen here in the Pacific Northwest. In the past month, I’ve been spending time pouring over a detailed map of the Teanaway Community Forest, where I’m designing the course for a &lt;a href=&quot;http://cascadeoc.org/event/ultimate-orienteer-7-score-o-2017/&quot;&gt;Score O&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/course-design-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view west from control 106&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course design is a bit like writing a school test. The subject matter is the mapped area and the challenges it presents: in this case, a wilderness area crisscrossed with trails and few major features other than the shape of the land to use for re-orienting in the field. I create problems for the competitors to solve, and while there may be no single right answer, I should reward those with the most advanced skills and understanding. I’ll try to avoid including dumb tricks, but do make competitors think twice about their decisions. I’m working to create an experience that is fair, fun, and fast. As a designer, the highest praise is a worn-out competitor who returns to the finish with a smile on their face, ecstatic to tell me about all the mistakes they made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite part about orienteering is the rush I get in the moment of realization that I’m not where I thought I was: I’m lost. Especially in wilderness, it’s amazing to take a couple seconds to enjoy the state of being &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt;, alone. Lost, but also fully equipped with the tools I need (a detailed map and a compass) to bring myself back to reality. Well, at least &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; enjoy it; friends tell me your experience my vary. With no controls in the field from which to benchmark while I’m scouting for my own course, I get to have this experience a bit more often. It slows me down, sure, but ultimately it’s why I’m here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/course-design-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The gnarly rootstock at control 173&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this three hour Score O event, I need to blanket controls over a wide area so that part of the challenge is choosing which checkpoints to visit within the event’s time limit. Ideally, even the fastest competitors (we have multiple Team USA members who frequent our meets) shouldn’t be able to clear the course. Scouting doesn’t happen at my race pace either - I need to be absolutely sure I’ve identified the correct locations or else I’ll find angry competitors complaining of a misplaced control at the finish. On my first trip to the venue, I spent close to ten hours zigging and zagging through the rolling hills, sometimes on trails, more often slipping between trees and through tall grass on the way to boulders or re-entrants with no trail in sight. I make mental notes and tie surveyor’s tape at my locations; I’ll be back in a week to set the actual controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day before the race I’m a little nervous; I need to cover a lot of area with control flags, stands, and the electronic punch boxes competitors use to record visiting a control. I’ve drawn up four loops for myself so that I don’t need to carry all the gear at once. These are my own little courses, and at least this time around I’ll find pink tape at each location for a confidence boost. I set three of the four loops in the afternoon sun while clouds speed by overhead. Occasional gusts threaten a storm that thankfully never materializes. On race day I wake up early to set out the last 10 controls. When it’s all done, I’ve spent nearly six hours placing equipment. Is it all in the right spot? Will anyone visit every control in half of that time? I’m about to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orienteering typically uses staggered starts where competitors leave the start at two minute intervals in order to discourage following. For Score O, because there is no prescribed control order, there is a mass start. As a designer, it’s the first chance for me to evaluate my design. As competitors frantically scribble on their maps (we had a ~5 minute planning period) and discard jackets they won’t need while running, I count down to the start. “One minute! 30 seconds! Ten! Three, two, one, Go! Have fun! Don’t get lost! Come back on time!” And just like that, I’m left standing alone at a gate where the pavement turns to gravel as 50 people scatter into the surrounding terrain. I smile as I count groups headed towards at least four different first controls, maybe five. Hopefully I’ll see smiles as they return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/course-design-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The view north from control 102&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple hours, I learn my fate. I’ve been defeated, the course has been cleared. There’s also a few reports that a control on the far end of the map is likely up to 200m off from where my map indicates. That’s frustrating for me to hear (and I know it was even more frustrating out on the course!) but luckily it’s not all bad news here. Finishers trickle in as the clock counts down, and it’s a jovial atmosphere as competitors discuss routes while they recover. I hear of the vistas, the amazing rock features, the subtle saddle. I share in the triumph of finding a difficult control on a small point feature in flat terrain, the sorrow in a route choice gone wrong, and the thrill of returning with seconds to spare. For me, all of this is a priceless reward. My work on designing and setting courses, once secrets, are now something I’ve shared with a community of which I’m grateful to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post Script:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can view the map and courses from this event at CascadeOC’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://rg.cascadeoc.org/rg2/#178&amp;amp;course=2&quot;&gt;route gadget&lt;/a&gt; tool.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While setting controls, I found across a large pile of ribbons in an area of forest off trail. This was very odd trash to find until I investigated a little further and discovered it was actually a message in a bottle that had been attached to some balloons! I contacted the sender, who reported they had launched it from Bellingham a few weeks earlier. I’ll never know if it was still floating in the sky during my scouting trip, or if I navigated within a few meters of it but missed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/course-design-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A home-made balloon message in a bottle. Glad I had a backpack to carry it out.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/05/25/creating-being-lost.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/05/25/creating-being-lost.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>For the Planet</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;This Saturday 22 April 2017 is the first &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marchforscience.com&quot;&gt;March for Science&lt;/a&gt;, an organized moment for people around the globe to gather in support evidence based discovery. I’ll be marching in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marchforscienceseattle.org/&quot;&gt;Seattle&lt;/a&gt;. Saturday is also Earth Day, a movement which saw its beginnings back in 1970 when millions of Americans rallied to support healthy, sustainable environmental choices. While both of these causes may have been born out of political frustration, their missions span those boundaries. No matter your opinion on &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; government and collective action can solve the myriad challenges that our Mother Earth faces today, I hope you’ll join me on Saturday at a March for Science or Earth Day event in your community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-i-march&quot;&gt;Why I March&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;science-is-a-framework&quot;&gt;Science is a Framework&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science, specifically the scientific method of hypothesis testing, is a broad problem solving framework applicable to problems across subjects, industries, and generations. It gives us structure to approach the unknown, and allows progress even in the light of failure. Science tells us to consider what we know, make a prediction, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9kf51FpBuXQ&quot;&gt;put it to the test&lt;/a&gt;. Often the prediction will be wrong. Often when an experiment is completed it may leave more questions than answers. As much as today’s society is all about answers and progress, new information is not a failure in the eye of Science. Where would we be if every negative result became a stop order? Edison reportedly failed &lt;a href=&quot;http://edison.rutgers.edu/newsletter9.html#4&quot;&gt;thousands of times&lt;/a&gt; while working on the incandescent light bulb and other inventions. I march because Science is a problem solving framework that helps us correct our mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;science-is-hard&quot;&gt;Science is Hard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science may adapt to help us learn from failure, but that doesn’t mean it’s easy. Science asks humans to be objective when observing and reporting results. As a pattern-seeking species, that task is incredibly difficult, even when experimental controls are in place. Many career scientists, even academics and others in public positions, have incentives that may compete with the guidelines that science provides for experiments. Publication quotas for tenured positions. Financial rewards or promotion for positive results. Journals favoring significant results over negative findings. (For the interested, I highly recommend this &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/science-isnt-broken/&quot;&gt;FiveThirtyEight piece about P-hacking&lt;/a&gt;.) Scientists can’t just be experts in their own field. Experiments bring up questions in statistics and ethics, and without a comprehensible and accurate summary, findings can fall flat. I march because the people who dedicate their lives to science deserve credit for more than discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-a-plan&quot;&gt;Make a Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wherever you participate on April 22, make a plan &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; for a couple key things and you’ll be more likely to get out there and stay a little happier on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get there.&lt;/strong&gt; Where does your event start? Which bus or train do you need to catch? Remember, a march is a gathering of people, not cars: if you can avoid it, don’t bring your car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find your friends, and make new connections.&lt;/strong&gt; It can be surprisingly difficult to navigate through a crowd to your friends. Don’t forget to take the time to talk with those around you. You all came out for a reason, don’t be afraid to find out what other folks are passionate about and you might find a new friend. Even small discussions can help others feel more involved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep yourself fueled.&lt;/strong&gt; Carry some food and water if you can, bonus points if you bring a little extra you can share. Also consider supporting local businesses along the march route.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check the weather.&lt;/strong&gt; You’re going to be outside. Thanks to radar and modeling, you’ll probably know if it’s going to be wet or cold. Bundle appropriately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-stop&quot;&gt;Don’t Stop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific method doesn’t end with a negative result. Every day is Earth Day. Use April 22 as a chance to find a community where you can continue to support the causes you care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8MqTOEospfo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/04/20/for-the-planet.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/04/20/for-the-planet.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>What's your Win of the Day?</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past week I built a little web app where anyone can come and record a win of the day. I hope this idea can grow into a nice bright corner of the internet. &lt;a href=&quot;https://WinOfTheDay.com&quot;&gt;Celebrate your Win of the Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/wotd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Small wins&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, writing down a win of the day is a great way to reflect and recharge. Sometimes it feels like everything is going wrong, but even on days like those I can find something positive to keep me going. It doesn’t have to be big or special, it’s OK to feel good about the little things too. Maybe I did some cleaning, or spent some time outside, or simply got out of bed. We all have those days. And on days when things are going great, it’s exciting to reflect and celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own strengths and weaknesses that are changing all the time. I built Win of the Day to never publicly attach a username to a win because this isn’t about competition. It’s about individuals each doing their best; it’s about finding happiness in the joy of success for you and for others, no matter how big or how small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;technical-notes&quot;&gt;Technical Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is yet another &lt;a href=&quot;http://flask.pocoo.org/&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; app, so I reused a lot of boilerplate code, but also tried a few new packages. This site allows users to login and also has some pages restricted to moderators, so I needed to implement an authentication and authorization scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; using social login for random web sites, so everything is happening in flask and my own database. Don’t worry, I didn’t write my own security - I’m &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salt_(cryptography)&quot;&gt;salting&lt;/a&gt; password values and using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bcrypt&quot;&gt;bcrypt&lt;/a&gt; library for hashing and password checking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of security and passwords, you’ve probably noticed that web browsers are starting to raise more alarms when the browser detects a form transmitting data over an insecure connection. Luckily, my web host makes it super easy to to generate and install certificates from &lt;a href=&quot;https://letsencrypt.org/&quot;&gt;Let’s Encrypt&lt;/a&gt;. With a certificate in place, the Flask-SSLify library makes it trivial to force requests to be made over https.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can browse the code on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ercjns/WinOfTheDay&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;. Feedback and pull requests welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/03/24/win-of-the-day.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/03/24/win-of-the-day.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A Quiet Approach to PM</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;One of my friends recently posted a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@nkkl/ballad-of-the-type-b-pm-33dfb4428a73&quot;&gt;short note&lt;/a&gt; about different PM archetypes that are explicitly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; Type A personalities. It really resonated with me. Go ahead and read it now (3 min), then come back here for a bit of my own thoughts and experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my first job out of college, I spent two and a half years as a Program Manager at Microsoft, working on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.windows.com&quot;&gt;Windows Developer Center&lt;/a&gt;, the backbone for Microsoft’s competitor to the Apple App Store and Google Play. The Microsoft PM culture I experienced places a higher value on winning than on helping - this didn’t sit well with me. A private note I wrote at the time is a good summary of my general approach to PM, a subtext to my frustrations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Listen to all of my teammates and find out individual, candid opinions of what’s great and what is bothersome. Never put my own opinion on a shining platter - it doesn’t have a special blessing just because I’m in the PM role. I don’t want to be calling all the shots - so I don’t, I make sure my team calls the shots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a facilitator and a strong believer that everyone is more productive when success is more than the result at the end of a series of checklists. I love the empathy driven aspect of program management - to discover and communicate user needs to the development team and to create a solution that satisfies those needs. I know I have a lot to learn from those around me, and so I choose to make the communication and discovery a two-way street, an opportunity for team learning. That might be my most radical step away from “traditional” Type A PM strategies - I happily hold court rather than issuing a decree on product direction. I’m not interested in personally winning - I’m here for the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In itself, PM as facilitator is not a novel approach, but I was surprised by how much I stood out. That said, I worked hard, stuck to my principles, and found success. During daily standup and in one-off interactions, I kept developers aware of a project’s impact, elevating the focus above checking off isolated tasks. Even when an aspect of my spec was lacking, developers I worked with often managed to get it right the first time through implementation. We hashed out functional designs on developers’ white boards rather than my own where they couldn’t be referenced during coding. I made my office a space where no question is a dumb question, a place for discussing ideas as well as prioritization. I worked well with developers, but interactions with the PM team were a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group who I most expected to sympathize with customer stories (and the supporting data) appeared surprisingly stubborn to me. Prioritization exercises were too often won by the loudest voice in the room. While team slogged through must-have features as we played catch-up to other app ecosystems, I heard more references to competitor designs than to telemetry of our own users. When more resources became available to build new competitive features, I took the chance to instead drive something internally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project I developed telemetry infrastructure and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://powerbi.microsoft.com&quot;&gt;Power BI&lt;/a&gt; dashboard so that individual PMs, developers, and business leaders could more easily drill into the details behind the KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) being reported to leadership. Bringing easily questioned cross-team data to PM fingertips was a win worthy of the repeated demos and celebratory e-mails. I felt good about the project’s success, but the bragging still felt out of place. To me, this was simply another way to help my teammates to do their best work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my last year at Microsoft, I reached out to one of my previous managers for mentorship. My manager at the time was sympathetic to and appreciative of my team-building approach to driving progress, but I wasn’t sure about how to approach others on the PM team - the culture still felt overly self-centered. I wanted new strategies to experiment with while still being my authentic, pensive, pondering, but deliberate, self. Show more data. Speak up more. Celebrate achievements. Advocate for yourself. The suggestions made sense as career advice, but were hard to reconcile with my identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My previous manager also mentioned that I wasn’t alone in my feelings: a respected colleague had decided to move on partly due to a similar internal conflict of helping versus winning. She delivered objectively great work, but had decided something wasn’t quite right. Helpfulness is a distinctly different feeling from the winning focus that seemed to fuel (and promote) my peers, and the latter had little appeal to me. I left Microsoft a few months after that conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does that leave the Type B PM? Every team, every company is different; not every pair will be a good fit. Of course, just as a great PM smoothly adapts a project to changing requirements and resource constraints, he (she) shouldn’t forget to also adapt himself (herself), and his (her) approaches. Find what your teammates need, and help them do it, whatever it takes. Be yourself, but also occasionally let go and &lt;em&gt;be someone who you never thought you’d be&lt;/em&gt;. I’m still experimenting with that last challenge - I like to think that every human is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cookie-cutter PM may be a Type A control freak, but diversity of approaches across a PM team can create value the same way diversity of backgrounds fuels creativity and openness through new perspectives. We all build delightful experiences by empathizing with users and wrangling teams to deliver, and every individual has their own way to be authentic and successful. It doesn’t always work out, and that’s a big part of why you’re there as a PM in the first place: to climb back aboard and get the wheels spinning again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And if you’re looking to add a PM to your team who values teammates just like customers, or know someone who is, I’d love to hear from you.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/03/03/quiet-approach-to-pm.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/life/2017/03/03/quiet-approach-to-pm.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Sharing Bicycles</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Bike share is a transportation option becoming more and more common around the world. Bicycles have always been a great method for combatting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Last_mile_(transportation)&quot;&gt;last mile&lt;/a&gt; problem in transportation, and while current technology has allowed bike share to become much more practical to operate, the idea of a community bike pool has been around for decades. Cities &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.velib.paris.fr/&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://topekametrobikes.org/&quot;&gt;all&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biketownpdx.com/&quot;&gt;sizes&lt;/a&gt;, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.republicbike.com/google_bikes.asp&quot;&gt;corporate&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.princeton.edu/main/news/archive/S45/95/35K87/index.xml?section=topstories&quot;&gt;college&lt;/a&gt; campuses have implemented bike share to help their communities move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/posts/pronto-01-station.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Pronto station at the Burke Gilman Trail near U Village.&quot; /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pronto Station UD-01 at the Burke Gilman Trail near U Village. Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sounderbruce/&quot;&gt;SounderBruce&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Seattle, there is a bit of a sour relationship with bike share. After about two and a half years of service, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.prontocycleshare.com/&quot;&gt;Pronto&lt;/a&gt; will close at the end of March, and plans for a possible replacement have been tabled. The Seattle Bike Blog has a ton of reporting on this, I suggest &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.seattlebikeblog.com/2016/02/04/pronto-needs-city-buyout-before-end-of-march-how-did-we-get-here/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; as a good place to start if you want all the history. There have been a number of reports about why bike share may have failed in Seattle, but that’s not my goal here. Instead, I’d like to take a positive spin. More often than not, bicycle riders, especially those on the heavy, cruiser style bikes that most modern bike share systems use, are smiling. Let’s take a look at the joy Pronto brought to Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enjoying-the-waterfront&quot;&gt;Enjoying The Waterfront&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer (and other seasons too!) you’ll find gobs of people passing time in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seattle.gov/parks/find/parks/myrtle-edwards-park&quot;&gt;Myrtle Edwards Park&lt;/a&gt; along the waterfront in lower Queen Anne, north of downtown. The folks at Proto knew this, and placed a station at the south end of the park, where Alaskan turns away from the water and the Elliott Bay Trail begins. Here’s a simple chart showing the number of rentals beginning at each station during 2015 and 2016. &lt;em&gt;WF-01&lt;/em&gt; at Alaskan Way and Clay, just a block from the Sculpture Park, was the starting point for nearly two thousand more rides than any other station over the two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:35px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://plot.ly/~ercjns/106/?share_key=QnTSge88Ub2y8NtAqVxUnA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Trips By Station&quot; style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://plot.ly/~ercjns/106.png?share_key=QnTSge88Ub2y8NtAqVxUnA&quot; alt=&quot;Trips By Station&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%;width: 600px; max-height: 500px;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; onerror=&quot;this.onerror=null;this.src='https://plot.ly/404.png';&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&quot;ercjns:106&quot; sharekey-plotly=&quot;QnTSge88Ub2y8NtAqVxUnA&quot; src=&quot;https://plot.ly/embed.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;joyrides&quot;&gt;Joyrides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shouldn’t come as a surprise that many of the riders departing from Alaskan and Clay also returned their bikes there. This station had the highest percentage of return trips with nearly 35% of trips starting and ending at &lt;em&gt;WF-01&lt;/em&gt;. But where else did users go for joyrides? Overall, 8.1% of trips started and ended at the same station, but four other stations had return rates over 20%, as shown below. Where are these stations? &lt;em&gt;DPD-03&lt;/em&gt; is at the Children’s Hospital on Sandpoint Way, where Pronto provided an opportunity for Doctors, Nurses, and Visitors to take a break and enjoy the nearby Burke Gilman Trail. &lt;em&gt;UD-01&lt;/em&gt; provided a similar opportunity for employees of U-Village and Ravenna/Bryant residents. The two other stations are in the heart of the U District: &lt;em&gt;UD-07&lt;/em&gt; at 47th and 12th and &lt;em&gt;UW-02&lt;/em&gt; at the Burke Museum on the NW corner of the UW campus. I won’t speculate on the possible activities but the beauty is that these stations all provided the joy of a spontaneous bike ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:35px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://plot.ly/~ercjns/108/?share_key=qUm19ZjrdB7YsGSsg5BVSl&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Pronto Round-Trips&quot; style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://plot.ly/~ercjns/108.png?share_key=qUm19ZjrdB7YsGSsg5BVSl&quot; alt=&quot;Pronto Round-Trips&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%;width: 600px; max-height: 500px;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; onerror=&quot;this.onerror=null;this.src='https://plot.ly/404.png';&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&quot;ercjns:108&quot; sharekey-plotly=&quot;qUm19ZjrdB7YsGSsg5BVSl&quot; src=&quot;https://plot.ly/embed.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;biking-with-friends&quot;&gt;Biking with Friends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riding just for riding is great, but riding with friends is even better! The Pronto data can’t capture when someone rents a Pronto bike to join a friend on a personal bike, but I can make some estimations about when groups rent Pronto bikes together. For my analysis, I looked for trips which started and ended at the same station, and which started and ended within two minutes of each other. There were plenty of pairs, but there were plenty of large groups too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A group of eight rode from The Space Needle (&lt;em&gt;SLU-22&lt;/em&gt;) to The Sculpture Park (&lt;em&gt;WF-01&lt;/em&gt;) at 8pm in August 2016 - just in time to see watch the sunset from the water!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A group of twelve (!) enjoyed the waterfront from Occidental Park (&lt;em&gt;PS-04&lt;/em&gt;) to the Sculpture Park (&lt;em&gt;WF-01&lt;/em&gt;) in June 2016.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A group of six chose Pronto bicycles for the six-block journey from 3rd and Broad (&lt;em&gt;BT-01&lt;/em&gt;) to 2nd and Vine (&lt;em&gt;BT-03&lt;/em&gt;). I’ll never know if they were just starting their night or ending a long day at 10pm on a Saturday night in August 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 242897 trips in my the dataset, 56403 (23.2%) were a trip made with Friends. Below you’ll see the distribution of group sizes. The distribution is as expected (tons of pairs, fewer as group size increases), but the real takeaway here is the sheer volume. Taken on average, every single day there was a group of four more enjoying cycling together using Pronto bikes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:35px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://plot.ly/~ercjns/104/?share_key=BfMErkpkmjqKg6VOxwArCb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Groups Histogram&quot; style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://plot.ly/~ercjns/104.png?share_key=BfMErkpkmjqKg6VOxwArCb&quot; alt=&quot;Groups Histogram&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%;width: 600px; max-height: 500px;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; onerror=&quot;this.onerror=null;this.src='https://plot.ly/404.png';&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&quot;ercjns:104&quot; sharekey-plotly=&quot;BfMErkpkmjqKg6VOxwArCb&quot; src=&quot;https://plot.ly/embed.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-joy-of-bicycles&quot;&gt;The Joy of Bicycles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is so much to love about bicycles: seeing new things! riding with friends! going fast! beating the bus! enjoying life! There’s a lot more joy to be found in this data, and I hope to periodically update this post with more findings. You can explore for yourself using the data available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.prontocycleshare.com/data&quot;&gt;http://www.prontocycleshare.com/data&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks, Pronto, for helping support the joy of bicycling in Seattle for the past two years.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/02/14/sharing-bicycles.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/02/14/sharing-bicycles.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Markov News</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been dreaming about ideas for a simple but off-hand useful (and fun!) twitter bot, and the ridiculous #fakenews sensation became an opportunity. Many people who have taken an intro computer science course are familiar with markov chains. Without getting too technical, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;markov chain&lt;/a&gt; is a process where the next outcome in the process, given the current state, is independent of past behavior, and where the possible outcomes are discrete known values. This algorithm turns out to be a great way to generate text that reads in a specific voice. (This isn’t a new trick - there are plenty of markov text generators around the web.)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/01/18/markov-news.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.ercjns.com/projects/2017/01/18/markov-news.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
